Guide to the Merrill Isely Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Merrill Isely Papers
1919-1961
RG 158
Yale University Divinity School Library
4.5
(10 boxes)
Correspondence to family members and others, dating from 1919 to 1961, provides detailed documentation of Isely's life and work in Turkey. Merrill Isely and his wife Mildred were missionaries serving under the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions in Gaziantep, Turkey for four decades beginning in 1920.
Isely, Merrill N.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Biographical / Historical
1894 Aug 4 Born in Fairview, Kansas
1916 B.A., Fairmount College
1916-1917 Attended Oberlin College
1920 B.D., Yale Divinity School
1920 Jun 14 Ordained as Congregational minister in Wichita, Kansas
1920-1960 Missionary of the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions in Gaziantep (Aintab), Turkey; served as business manager of the Azariah Smith Memorial Hospital. His wife, Mildred, served there as dietician. Isely was also involved in a reforestation project, persuading the Turkish government to start a tree-growing project in Gaziantep, as well as in bee-keeping and other agricultural projects.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists primarily of letters written by Merrill Isely to family members and friends in the United States. Regular, detailed letters describe Isely's life and work in Turkey. Writings and reports provide extensive information about the American Board hospital in Gaziantep (Aintab), Turkey. These papers complement the papers of Albert Dewey found in YDSL Record Group No. 161. Dewey was a colleague of the Iselys at the Gaziantep station.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence,1919-1961, n.d.
II. Writings and Reports, 1919-1961, n.d.
III. Personal Items and Memorabilia, 1920-1932, n.d.
Missions -- Turkey; Missionaries; Isely, Merrill N.; American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions
- Correspondence, 1919-1961, n.d.; Series I
  - Family Correspondence
    - Merrill Isely to family in the U.S., 1919-1923 (Box 1, Folder 1-13)
    - Merrill Isely to family in the U.S., 1924-1926 Jul (Box 2, Folder 14-22)
    - Merrill Isely to family in the U.S., 1926 Aug-1930 Oct (Box 3, Folder 23-31)
    - Merrill Isely to family in the U.S., 1930 Nov-1933 Mar (Box 4, Folder 32-39)
    - Merrill Isely to family in the U.S., 1933 Apr-1938 (Box 5, Folder 40-49)
    - Merrill Isely to family in the U.S., 1939 -1942 Feb (Box 6, Folder 50-58)
    - Merrill Isely to family in the U.S., 1942 Mar-1961 (Box 7, Folder 59-70)
  - General Correspondence
    - A (Box 8, Folder 71)
    - B (Box 8, Folder 72)
    - Belcher, H. (Box 8, Folder 73)
    - Birge, J. (Box 8, Folder 74)
    - C (Box 8, Folder 75)
    - Case, H. (Box 8, Folder 76)
    - Clark, A. (Box 8, Folder 77)
    - D (Box 8, Folder 78)
    - Darling, H. (Box 8, Folder 79)
    - Dewey, A. (Box 8, Folder 80)
    - E (Box 8, Folder 81)
    - Eddy, B. (Box 8, Folder 82)
    - Emerson, M. (Box 8, Folder 83)
    - F (Box 8, Folder 84)
    - Finlayson, J. (Box 8, Folder 85)
    - Fowle, L. (Box 8, Folder 86)
    - G (Box 8, Folder 87)
    - Gonzalez, J. (Box 8, Folder 88)
    - Goodsell, F. (Box 8, Folder 89)
    - Guludge, E. (Box 8, Folder 90)
    - H (Box 8, Folder 91)
    - Hamilton, C. (Box 8, Folder 92)
    - I (Box 8, Folder 93)
    - J (Box 8, Folder 94)
    - K (Box 8, Folder 95)
    - L (Box 8, Folder 96)
    - M (Box 8, Folder 97)
    - Meeken, H. (Box 8, Folder 98)
    - Merrill, J. (Box 8, Folder 99)
    - N (Box 9, Folder 100)
    - O (Box 9, Folder 101)
    - Ober, F. (Box 9, Folder 102)
    - P (Box 9, Folder 103)
    - R (Box 9, Folder 104)
    - Randall, H. (Box 9, Folder 105)
    - Riggs, E. (Box 9, Folder 106)
    - S (Box 9, Folder 107)
    - Small, A. (Box 9, Folder 108)
    - Smith, R. (Box 9, Folder 109)
    - T (Box 9, Folder 110)
    - U (Box 9, Folder 111)
    - Uline, M. (Box 9, Folder 112)
    - V (Box 9, Folder 113)
    - W (Box 9, Folder 114)
    - Walkingwreners (Box 9, Folder 115)
    - Wells, C. (Box 9, Folder 116)
    - Wheatshockers (Box 9, Folder 117)
  - Support Letters
    - Letters, 1920-1961 (Box 9, Folder 118-120)
- Writings and Reports Material, 1919-1961, n.d.; Series II
  - Sermons, devotional writings by Merrill Isely, 1939-1944, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 122)
  - Reports and brochures re. American Board hospital in Gaziantep (Aintab) and the Turkey Mission, 1919-1961 (Box 10, Folder 123)
  - "Gaziantep Power House Notes" - mimeographed circulars, 1931-1940 (Box 10, Folder 124-128)
  - Statistical reports re. Gaziantep station (Box 10, Folder 129)
  - Material re. rural missions, agricultural projects (Box 10, Folder 130)
  - Material re. Turkey and Aleppo College in Syria (Box 10, Folder 131)
  - Material re. Turkey (Box 10, Folder 132)
  - Maps (Box 10, Folder 133)
  - Miscellaneous reports, notes (Box 10, Folder 134)
- Personal Items and Memorabilia, 1920-1932, n.d.; Series III
  - Diary of Merrill Isely, 1920-1922 (Box 10, Folder 135)
  - Biographical material, incl. re. trial of Merrill Isely on charge of illegally conducting religious worship, 1932, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 136)
  - Programs from mission and family events (Box 10, Folder 137)
  - Newspaper clippings re. Iselys (Box 10, Folder 138-139)